Prelminary Guide to the Stephen S. Wise papers, 1905-1977 K0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Stephen S. Wise papers
1905-1953
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Wise, Stephen Samuel
K0002
1 Linear Feet
Series one consists of correspondence primarily to and from Stephen S. Wise. There are nearly two hundred letters dating from 1905-1953, with the bulk of correspondence from 1907-32. Series two consists of diaries, notes, addresses, and research guides related to Stephen S. Wise from 1908-1952, with the bulk of materials from 1908-1927. Included are three sets of personal diaries ranging from 1910-14 and 1921-22, notes from his trip to Palestine in 1922, and a number of undated writings on scrap paper. There is also a twenty-eight page bibliography on the writings of Wise. Series three consists of general newsclippings and pamphlets, as well as invitations and programs of events relating to Stephen S. Wise, dating from 1909-1977, with the bulk of materials from 1911-1940.
Box 2
Box 1
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
In 1996, I. Edward Kiev's personal library was donated to the Gelman Library at the George Washington University and the papers of Stephen S. Wise were included with the original donation
Biographical Note
Stephen Samuel Wise (1874-1949) was born in Budapest, Hungary, and came to the United States the following year. In America, his father Rabbi Aaron Wise and the esteemed rabbis, Alexander Kohut and Gustav Gottheil prepared him for the rabbinate. At the age of eighteen, he graduated with honors from Columbia University and a year later, in 1893, he was ordained in Austria by the Chief Rabbi of Vienna, Adolph Jellinek.
"The People's Rabbi," as Wise would later be known, developed his deep concern for the less fortunate at an early age. When he was seven years old Wise heard of the government sponsored pogroms inflicted upon the Jews in Czarist Russia. This incident would open his eyes to the suffering of the poor and the powerless. Wise, who would enjoy the reputation as one of the century's finest orators, established a connection with the masses. In true liberal spirit, Wise fought for housing projects, the abolition of child labor, the improvement of working conditions, securing rights for female workers and equal rights for African Americans, and was a co-founder of both the National Association of the Advancement of Colored People [NAACP] and the American Civil Liberties Union [ACLU]. Wise began his Zionist career during the nascence of the movement in the 1890s. Wise, like Theodor Herzl, the father of modern Zionism, was outraged by the 1894 trial of French Captain Alfred Dreyfus who was accused of treason, falsely convicted and not exonerated until 1906, resulting in a shared conviction that the Jewish people required a homeland. Wise helped to organize its supporters and communicate the movement's ideology. He founded the New York Federation of Zionist Societies in 1987, which led to the nationwide Federation of American Zionists in 1898, and was a founder of the World Jewish Congress. Later, Wise was a leader in the American Jewish Congress, president and vice president of the Zionist Organization of America and an important liaison to American Presidents, such as Woodrow Wilson and Franklin Delano Roosevelt.
In 1900, Wise accepted the post of rabbi at Temple Beth Israel in Portland, Oregon, the same year he married Louise Waterman. He remained in Oregon for six years where he threw himself into "Good Government," pressing for reform in state and city politics. He pioneered in interfaith cooperation, social service, and civic leadership, which included his non-paid position as Commissioner of Child Labor for Oregon. In 1906, Wise first sprang into national prominence. In his famous, "Open Letter to the Members of Temple Emanu-El of New York on the Freedom of the Jewish Pulpit," he rejected the offer to serve as rabbi of the prestigious Temple Emanu-El of New York because his demand for a "free pulpit," one that was not subject to control by a board of trustees, was refused. A year later, he returned from Oregon to New York and founded the Free Synagogue, which had free pews to all without fixed dues and maintained an extensive program of social welfare. Most importantly, Wise established a pulpit where the rabbi had the autonomy to promote social welfare, criticize inaction, and encouraged the use of religion as the remedy to society's ills. Like his Christian colleagues Walter Rauschenbusch, Josiah Strong, and Washington Gladden, Wise was a bold and influential preacher of public concerns.
Among Wise's proudest achievements was his establishment of the Jewish Institute of Religion [JIR] in 1922 in New York City, a rabbinical seminary which merged with Hebrew Union College in 1950. Wise became a mentor to a young Isaac Edward Kiev who began his studies at the seminary in 1924 and gave Kiev a job in the JIR Library to help pay for school. The relationship between Wise and Kiev grew and Kiev became Chief Librarian in 1943, where he remained until his death in 1975. In 1996, I. Edward Kiev's personal library was donated to the Gelman Library at the George Washington University and the papers of Stephen S. Wise were included with the original donation.
Stephen S. Wise died in 1949 in New York City.
The Stephen S. Wise Papers, containing 191 boxes, are housed at the American Jewish Historical Society [AJHS], AJHS Manuscript Catalog, #P-134
Collection Scope and Content
Series one consists of 0.5 linear feet of correspondence to, from, and about Stephen S. Wise. The letters are arranged into subseries according to general topic, and alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent within each subseries. There are nearly two hundred letters dating from 1905-1953, with the bulk of correspondence from 1907-32. The letters are primarily written in English with some in Hebrew and German. Correspondents include many prominent Jewish rabbis, scholars, laymen, and philanthropists, primarily from the New York area, as well as notable non-Jewish authors, politicians, and religious figures.
Series two consists of 0.25 linear feet of diaries, notes, and addresses written by Stephen S. Wise as well as research guides relating to Stephen S. Wise dating from 1908-1952, with the bulk of materials from 1908-1927. Included are three sets of personal diaries ranging from 1910-14 and 1921-22, notes from his trip to Palestine in 1922, and a number of undated writings on scrap paper. There is also a twenty-eight page bibliography on the writings of Wise.
Series three consists of general newsclippings and pamphlets, as well as invitations and programs of events relating to Stephen S. Wise, dating from 1909-1977, with the bulk of materials from 1911-1940.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings, and Ephemera.
Bib#
12212717
World War, 1914-1918; Social justice; Women's rights; Reform Judaism; Jewish Community of New York City; United States; Palestine; Immigration; Israel; Social reformers; Zionism; World War, 1939-1945; Jewish religious schools; Jews, American; Judaism; Wise, Stephen Samuel; Jewish Institute of Religion (New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence, 1905-1953; 1907-1932; K0002 Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Series one consists of 0.5 linear feet of correspondence to, from, and also about Stephen S. Wise. There are nearly two hundred letters dating from 1905-1953, with the bulk of correspondence from 1907-32. The letters are primarily written in English with some Hebrew and German. Correspondents include many prominent Jewish rabbis, scholars, laymen, and philanthropists, primarily from the New York area, as well as notable non-Jewish authors, politicians, and religious figures.
  Arrangement Note
  The letters are arranged into subseries according to general topic, and alphabetically arranged by name of correspondent within each subseries.
  - Jewish Institute of Religion, 1923-1945; 1923-1932
    Scope and Contents
    Most of the correspondence in this subseries relates to the Jewish Institute of Religion Library and especially concerns the acquisition and transfer of books. Correspondents include potential donors or sellers of books and representatives of other educational institutions as well as Jewish Institute of Religion faculty. Some letters also discuss Jewish Institute of Religion personnel matters and educational practices.
    - Baron, Salo, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Berkson, Isaac B., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bloch, Joshua, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bryan, Mary B., 1926 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cohen, Martha, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Farber, R., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Fischbein, Morris, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gordon, H.L., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hertz, Emanuel, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Hübsen, Adele, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Kalisch, Samuel, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Kohut, George Alexander, 1925-1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      General note
      Includes Kohut's correspondence with Andrew Keogh and Emanuel Hertz as well as correspondence concerning the Alexander Kohut Memorial Foundation and the Kohut Memorial Collection at the Yale University Library.
    - Langstadter, Rosetta, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Loeb, James, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Obermann, Julian, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Ogden, Charles J., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Oko, Adolf S., 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Also includes discussion of the Domus Spinozana Foundation, of which Oko served as Trustee.
    - Pearson, Leonard S., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Russell, Howard G., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Shapiro, Israel, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Shire, Sadie L., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Sternheim, Emanuel, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Thackeray, Henry St. John, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Torrey, Charles C., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Wagner-Tauber, Lina, 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Wise, Jonah B., 1925-1926 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Four letters with illegible or incomplete signatures concerning the Jewish Institute of Religion Library or other J.I.R. business, 1924-1925 and undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Free Synagogue, 1907-1925
    The correspondence in this subseries consists of letters from Jewish community leaders expressing enthusiasm for or discussing speaking invitations to the Free Synagogue, as well as inquiries from journalists and members of the public.
    - Brody, Ester, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Broido, Louis, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Ehrenreich, Bernard C., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Fleischer, Charles, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Frank, Rose L., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Freifeld, Samuel, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Guggenheimer, Fred L., 1925 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Hirsch, Emil G., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Schiff, Jacob H., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Seligman, Isaac N., 1907-1911 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Straus, Oscar S. (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Swett, Isaac, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Weil, Isaac J., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Wise, Leo, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Signature illegible, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Jewish Community Affairs, 1911-1921
    Correspondence in this subseries includes letters referencing controversies within Jewish community organizations and evaluating candidates for Jewish community leadership positions.
    - Keller, Max, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Krass, Nathan, c. 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Gottheil, Richard, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      General
      Letter to Louis Waterman Wise discussing Jacques Faitlovitch and his efforts on behalf of Ethiopian Jews.
    - Kohut, George Alexander, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Meyer, Martin A., 1917, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Includes discussion of Louis I. Newman and the Intercollegiate Menorah Association.
    - Wise, Leo, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Palestine/ Israel, 1910-1927
    Correspondence in this subseries discusses Zionist organizations and political developments affecting Pre-State Palestine.
    - Gottheil, Richard, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Weisgal, Meyer W., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Wise, Leo, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Political and Social Reform Activities, 1907-1953; 1907-1921
    - American Jewish Congress, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Press release, September 14, 1953: "Rabbis Goldstein and Eisendrath Score House Committee's Publication of Ex-Communist Testimony That Dr. Wise and Dr. Magnes Were Pro-Communist as Betrayal of Tenets of Public Responsibility and Decency"
    - Newton D. Baker, 1920-19211 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      Letters discuss rehabilitation of World War I veterans.
    - Billikopf, Jacob, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      Discussion of American Jewish industrial and economic leaders' interest in Poland's post- World War I reconstruction.
    - Borah, William E., 1911 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Deutsch, Gotthard, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      Discussion of humanitarian concerns regarding economic conditions in the former Austro-Hungarian territories.
    - Fosdick, Raymond B., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      Regarding the Henry Street Settlement and the application of Wise's Free Synagogue idea to social work in the Lower East Side.
    - Fritz, Edward M., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      Letter to Wise from Jewish Army officer during World War I.
    - Kahn, Otto H., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Knecht, Marcel, 1917 and undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Lawrence, David, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Lyons, Leo J., 1912 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Montague, Richard W., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Putnam, Irving, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Schiff, Jacob H., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Simon, John, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Singer, Jules B., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Straus, Lina and Nathan, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Wise, Jonah B., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Illegible or lost signatures, 1909-1920 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Interfaith Relations, 1907-1921 and undated
    - Brooks, William H., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Grosvenor, William M., 1910 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Lockhart, Arthur, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Macdonald, George, No year given (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Manning, William T., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Ullo, Lorenzo, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Williams, Charles D., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Illegible signature, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Arts and Letters, 1905-1945; 1917-1928
    - Bates, Katharine Lee, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Ben-Avi, Ittamar, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Brandeis, Louis, D., 1927 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Buber, Martin and Wilhelm, Y.D., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Davidson, (No First Name), 1908 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Ehrlich, Arnold B., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Margolis, Max L., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Obermann, Julian, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - O'Kane, Walter C., 1917 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Richards, Bernard G., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Ross, G.A. Johnston, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Incomplete Signature: "R.W.M.", 1924 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Personal, 1909-1921
    - Mack, (first name lost) W., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Ranson, Marius, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Stern, Richard M., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Straus, Nathan, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Wiezmann and Stein, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Wise, Leo, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 96)
    - Wise, Louise Waterman, c. 1913 (Box 1, Folder 97)
    - Wise, James W., 1909 - c. 1913 (Box 1, Folder 98)
    - Wise, Justine, 1909-1910 and undated (Box 1, Folder 99)
    - Illegible signature, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - General Correspondence, c. 1907-1924
    - Gutmann (No First Name), c. 1907 (Box 1, Folder 101)
    - Signature illegible- possibly Spak, S. F., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 102)
    - Illegible signature, Undated (Box 1, Folder 103)
- Writings, 1910-1977; 1910-1940; K0002 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 2)
  Series two consists of 0.25 linear feet of diaries, notes, and addresses written by Stephen S. Wise as well as research guides relating to Stephen S. Wise dating from 1908-1952, with the bulk of materials from 1908-1927.
  Included are three sets of personal diaries ranging from 1910-14 and 1921-22, notes from his trip to Palestine in 1922, and a number of undated writings on scrap paper. There is also a twenty-eight page bibliography on the writings of Wise.
  - Diaries, 1910-1914, 1921-1922
    - Diary of Stephen S. Wise, November 9, 1910 to December 2, 1914, 1910-1914 (Box 2, Folder 104a)
      The most complete of the three similar copies, this item was received by the Kiev Collection enclosed in a three-ring binder whose front cover was lost.
    - Diary of Stephen S. Wise, November 9, 1910 to January 19, 1913, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 104b)
      This copy is less complete than item 104a. The paper size and formatting also differs from the 104a copy, although the content is otherwise the same.
    - Diary of Stephen S. Wise, November 9, 1910 to January 19, 1913, 1910-1913 (Box 2, Folder 104c)
      Initial pages are torn, fragmentary. This item was received by the Kiev Collection enclosed in an album cover.
    - Diary of Stephen S. Wise, October 27, 1921 to April 18, 1922, 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 105)
      This item was received by the Kiev Collection enclosed in a three-ring binder.
  - Pamphlets, Lectures, and Sermons, 1923-1927 and undated
    - Addresses by Stephen S. Wise, Nathan Krass, and Sydney Goldstein, Union Service of the Federated Central and Free Synagogues, Carnegie Hall, May 6, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      Photocopy included in folder.
    - "'Shall the Doors be Shut?' or What Shall be the American Immigration Policy?", January 20, 1924 ( (Box 2, Folder 107)
      Address delivered by Stephen S. Wise at Carnegie Hall.
    - Pamphlet: "Forward" by Stephen S. Wise, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      Imprint: Vienna, 1927
    - "Toward Collective Security for Jews", c. 1930s (Box 2, Folder 109)
      Three pages, marked "Copy", typed on American Jewish Congress letterhead.
  - Handwritten Fragments and Notes, 1908-1925
    - Handwritten fragment: "What has Israel given to the World?", January 31, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 110)
      Draft of address or Free Synagogue sermon probably delivered at Clinton Hall, written on Lewis and Clark Centennial Exposition letterhead.
    - Handwritten fragment: "Our Own People: Questions of Jewish (illegible) or Racial (text lost)", October 1912 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Journal Notes, Palestine, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 112)
      Envelope containing typed and handwritten noteslips. Most are undated, some enclosed in paper tab marked, "Journal notes, Palestine, 1922".
  - Bibliography and Research Guides, 1952 and undated
    - List of Stephen S. Wise Correspondence in the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, June 3, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 113)
      14 pages listing 196 items.
    - Bibliography of Stephen S. Wise, Undated (Box 2, Folder 114)
      Two 28-page copies. Folder includes two additional copies of the first six pages.
- Ephemera, c. 1909-1977 and undated [bulk 1911-1940]; 1911-1940; 0.25 Linear feet
  Series three consists of general newsclippings and pamphlets, as well as invitations and programs of events relating to Stephen S. Wise, dating from 1909-1977, with the bulk of materials from 1911-1940.
  - Clippings, 1912, 1977, and undated (c. 1909-c. 1925)
    - Discussion of Christian Register article "Our Own People" (Samuel M. Crothers) on the subject of charity, May 9, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 115)
      Publication title lost.
    - "Strauss seeks no support as a Jew nor does he think support should be withheld because of his faith", September 22 (no year) (Box 2, Folder 116)
      Discusses Progressive nominee for governor of New York Strauss.
    - "Our great claim to the gratitude of mankind is that we gave to the world the Word of God…", Undated (Box 2, Folder 117)
      Fragment of news clipping.
    - "Vote for Joseph C. Pelletier for Governor", Undated (Box 2, Folder 118)
      Publication information lost. Boston article argues that candidate has demonstrated fairness toward Jews.
    - New York Evening Telegram article defending the New York Police Department's handling of the shooting of Herman Rosenthal, July 17 (no year) (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - "Rabbi Wise Tells Why So Many Marriages Fail", Undated (Box 2, Folder 120)
      Photocopy, no publication title.
    - "30 Years after death of Stephen Wise, his achievements are still neglected", April 3, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 121)
      Rabbi David Polish, The Jewish Week-American Examiner, April 3, 1977, p. 6.
  - Programs, 1934, 1940
    - Table assignment pamphlet (including alphabetical list of guests) for sixtieth birthday celebration of Stephen S. Wise hosted by the Free Synagogue and the Jewish Institute of Religion, New York, March 18, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Program for Stephen S. Wise's sixtieth birthday celebration dinner hosted by the Citizen's Committee, New York, March 19, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 123)
      Speakers included Albert Einstein and Fiorello LaGuardia.
    - Free Synagogue Weekly Bulletin, March 14, 1940 (vol. XXXII, no. 28), announcing a "special service and birthday celebration in honor of D. Stephen S. Wise) scheduled March 17, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Pamphlets, 1911-1922
    - "Politics and Morals", address by Woodrow Wilson, Governor of the State of New Jersey, April 1911 (Box 2, Folder 125)
      Folder includes envelopes marked "Farewell to Wilson", "The American Jewish Relief Committee for Sufferers from the War", "Woodrow Wilson", and "[text lost] Safe Deposit Co."
    - Signature page, Eastern Council of Reform Rabbis, New York, April 22, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 126)
      Photocopy
    - "The President's Flag Day Address with Evidence of Germany's Plans", September 15, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 127)
      Issued by the Committee on Public Information, the United States Secretaries of State, War, the Navy, and George Creel.
    - United States House Resolution 196, December 13, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 128)
      Submitted by Congressman Lunn to congratulate the people of Great Britain on the capture of Jerusalem.
    - Fragment of document discussing the Woodrow Wilson Foundation (established in 1922), Undated (Box 2, Folder 129)